Here's what we want to try to solve first.
When you go to a new form, what do we typically want to do?
We want to autofocus on the first text input.
That's fairly common.
But the question, of course, is how do we actually do that thing?
And so typically what you might do is you might throw an autofocus on the development.
That sometimes works, but then we know that with JavaScript loading and stuff, things get a little bit funky.
So what we're going to learn right now is to how to actually add autofocus to forms
in a way that is consistent and works.
What we want is the name to be the first thing that we focus on.
And so the thing about reactive references is that they work both in the data context
and they work in the template context.
So in other words, if we want an actual HTML element to be a reference,
we just tell it what the reference is going to be called.
So in this case, I usually like to preface any element that's going to be an actual element with EL.
So this is kind of back to the jQuery days.
We might preface it with a dollar symbol.
I just prefer to keep it consistent that way.
And then I'll call this like name input, for example.
And the way this works is up here inside of our reactive data, though, we do need to define it, though.
And how do we define that?
Well, we have this element called name input.
And it's going to be a reactive reference just like the reference in the template.
But we can actually tell it that it's going to be an HTML input element.
Or we can say it's, I think, null is the one that's typically an option.
Because here's the thing.
When JavaScript is loading, this thing does not exist.
So it has to be able to be null.
However, we do know once it's loaded, it will basically put an input element in there.
And so that's why believe it or not, that's all it takes for this thing to exist.
So if I log right now, log, whoops, that was a wrong name input, save it.
So you'll see that if I go to the new page, you'll see that it's already fetching that input automatically.
I don't have to go on-mounted, check to see if that element exists, assign it to the rough,
like that's just it's there, it works.
And that's kind of a little bit of the magic sprinkling that view does for us,
by assigning that rough to here.
So it looks to map those two things.
So that's a key thing to understand.
Okay, now that we have this, we can say,
when everything has been mounted properly,
so we'll call our on-mounted lifecycle hook, there we go.
So when you have it mounted, what your initial thought is probably going to say,
okay, well, I have a name input and I'm just going to run focus on it.
But as we see here, TypeScript is yelling at us because, again,
we've said that it might be null, it might not be defined.
So what I tried to do earlier here is I was like, okay,
well, we can check, right?
Like, you typically would, but if it exists, then just run this thing.
But it's kind of being finicky because I think it's either the way,
like the HTML element is being populated, like the truthy value.
So the way this actually works is you actually want to provide a question mark at it.
So we want to actually unpack the value because we don't forget,
element name input is a reactive reference.
It's not just, and it's still reactive reference,
even though it's referring to a div element.
But more importantly, this value here, it could be null.
So by putting the question mark here, I think this is, I want to say,
this is just vanilla JavaScript.
It basically, option or chaining,
checks to make sure this thing is valid before doing the next thing.
Although it makes me wonder now real quick,
I want to test this because I, if element input dot value,
would that have done it?
Ah, that works too.
So that's the key.
So this is where the unwrapping, that's why I say,
I want to people to get used to seeing that,
is because it's easy to forget this to be honest.
And so I was just like, oh yeah, it's definitely,
it's element value.
Now it's, it's dot value.
This, this works.
But I gotta say, there is something clean about just saying,
whenever this thing is available, just, just use it.
So option or chaining here is a pretty nice solution for this.
Now when we refresh the page and go to new,
you can see automatically focused.